Guide to the Records of the Research Institute for the Study of Man's (RISM) Medical and Social Anthropological Research in Bolivia RISM.RG.8
New York University Archives
Records of the Research Institute for the Study of Man's (RISM) Medical and Social Anthropological Research in Bolivia
1935-2006
1964-1967
New York University Archives
Research Institute for the Study of Man
RISM.RG.8
222.6 Linear Feet in 62 manuscript boxes, 7 half manuscript boxes, 7 card boxes, 83 box binders, 4 custom boxes, 39 record cartons, 156 shoe boxes, 1 flat box, and 1 flat file folder
The Research Institute for the Study of Man Bolivia Project was conducted between 1964 and 1967 at the request of the Peace Corps. The project was organized and led by Vera D. Rubin, founder and director of the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM), and Lambros Comitas, assistant director of RISM. Under their direction, multiple anthropological and epidemiological teams studied six ecologically distinct communities in Bolivia in order to identify major health problems and to assess the implications of rural social organization to facilitate the work of development agencies. The collection dates from 1935 to 2006, with the bulk of the material dating between 1964 and 1967. The collection documents the work of the project teams in Bolivia, and includes correspondence, accounting records, indexed field notes, laboratory processing records, surveys and questionnaires, maps, photographs, and films. The collection also includes materials from a 1997 exhibition, Retrospect and Prospect: Preservation and Use of Archival Materials in the Digital Age, about the Bolivia Project and the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions, with the exception of materials in Subseries IV. F. Blood Samples: Blood Typing Cards. Repository permission is required for access to material in Subseries IV. F. Please contact New York University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials associated with the Bolivia Project were created by teams of epidemiological and ethnographic researchers between 1964 and 1967 and transferred to the New York University Archives in 2006. In 2017 an accretion of correspondence was transferred to the archives by the Reed Foundation; the accession number associated with this gift is 2017.020.
Historical Note
In 1964, an intensive three-year medical-anthropological research program in Bolivia was undertaken by the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) at the request of the United States Peace Corps and in cooperation with the Bolivian Ministry of Public Health. The program was conducted under contract with the United States Peace Corps and received significant supplementary support from RISM. The goal of the research was to provide basic information for the development of public health and sanitation programs. Project administration was carried out by RISM director Vera D. Rubin and associate director Lambros Comitas, along with William J. McEwen, who served as the project research director, and Abdel Omran, who was director of the epidemiological research. The project had two interrelated research objectives: The epidemiological team attempted to define the major problems of health and disease in rural Bolivian communities, taking into account the drastically different ecological regions of the country. The communities surveyed included Villa Abecia, Coroico, Reyes, Sorata, Compi, and San Miguel. Clinical studies were conducted on a sample of 3,000 subjects to determine the incidence of tuberculosis and parasitic infections, the major endemic diseases affecting the region, and of nutritional and health status. Simultaneously, the ethnographic team conducted community studies in the same areas to provide background data on social and cultural features with special regard to attitudes toward health and disease and the structure of local institutions in the rural communities. Over eighty medical and social scientists, field workers, nurses, data analysts, and staff in the United States and Bolivia contributed to the project. Quarterly reports describing the work and the course of research were filed with the Peace Corps. Results and analysis were published in two companion volumes: the epidemiological report, Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia, was published by RISM in 1967, and the ethnographic report, Changing Rural Bolivia, was published by RISM in 1969 and as Changing Rural Society in 1971 by Oxford University Press. In addition, a number of articles, reports, theses and doctoral dissertations resulted from the project research.
Scope and Contents
The Records of the Research Institute for the Study of Man's Medical and Social Anthropological Research in Bolivia documents the work of anthropological and epidemiological teams in Bolivia and dates between 1935 and 2006, with the bulk of the material dating between 1964 and 1967. Material in the collection includes correspondence, accounting records, indexed field notes, laboratory processing records, surveys and questionnaires, maps, photographs, and films. The bulk of the collection consists of field notes taken by investigators in the course of their work, indexed cards created from these notes, and surveys and questionnaires conducted by the investigators. The field notes contain detailed observations of the day to day activities of the investigators, including their first impressions of the communities in which they lived, their interactions with residents of the communities, and maps and drawings of the communities. The indexed cards consist of photocopies of these notes that were organized by coded topics and cut and pasted onto cards according to these codes. The questionnaires include information about the health of the members of the communities, their living arrangements, and their opinions of social and political structures within the community. The surveys include information about sanitation, water supply, and livestock in the communities. Other material in the collection includes laboratory results of blood typing tests and blood and stool sampling for infectious diseases, maps of the six communities studied, census data for the six communities, photographs taken by the investigators, reports and papers written using the data generated through the project, and material created for a 1997 exhibit about the project and its records.
Custodial History
As of summer 2019, materials in Subseries IV. G. and H. and Subseries E. and F. are missing.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 13 series, some of which have been further arranged into subseries. The series are as follows:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Accounting Records
Series III. Indexes
Series IV. Epidemiological Research Records
Series V. Ethnographic Research Records
Series VI. Surveys and Questionnaires
Series VII. Unpublished Manuscripts
Series VIII. Community and Regional Maps
Series IX. Photographs
Series X. Audiovisual Materials
Series XI. Exhibition Material
Series XII. Reports from RISM to the Peace Corps, Partial Reports Related to the RISM Bolivia Project
Series XIII. Miscellaneous Papers
Appraisal
In 2020 several boxes containing duplications of other materials contained in the collection were deaccessioned. These materials include parts of Series VII and VIII which were microform copies of materials from Series III as well as Appendix: Photocopies which included copies of materials from Series IV and V.
Correspondence.; Ethnology -- Bolivia.; Coroico (Bolivia); Field notes.; Villa Abecia (Bolivia); Sorata (Bolivia); Bolivia -- Economic conditions -- 1952-1982.; Bolivia -- Politics and government -- 1952-1982.; Bolivia -- Rural conditions.; Bolivia -- Social conditions -- Research.; Bolivia -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Comitas, Lambros; McEwen, William J.; Peace Corps (U.S.); Novick, Victor; Rockefeller Foundation; Rubin, Vera D.; Torre, Mottram; Omran, Abdel R.; Bolivia. Ministerio de Salud y Deportes
- Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1997; 3.75 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 3 half manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence relating to various phases of the project, arranged alphabetically by the correspondents' last names or subject matter. Also included in this series are final reports, telegrams, clippings, budget papers, notes, memorandum, film strips, articles, and curriculum vitae that are referenced in the correspondence.
  - Administrative: Notes and Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative: Notes and Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnes, Katherine, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beltran, Aguirre, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bernhard, Bambi, Jul 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Berkeley Office and Personnel, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bibliography, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bolivia Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bolivia Office and Personnel, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Budgets, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book Information and Orders, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Budgets, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Buechler, Harris, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - C (General Correspondence), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Champeau, Catherine (Cathy), 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "C.R.B." Contracts and Royalty Statements, 1969, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Changing Rural Bolivia, Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Changing Rural Bolivia, Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings and Articles, Bolivia, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Clippings and Articles, Miscellaneous, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clinica Americana, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Code Books, Bolivia Survey, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Colmen, Joseph (Dr.), 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Comitas, Lambros, undated-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Conferences, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Coroico Team, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Danielson, David, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Data system, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Data system (epidemiology), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Educational References, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Erikson, Edwin, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Epidemiology Study Codes and Lists of Communities and Subcommunities, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Epidemiology Study: Correspondence (related to final report), 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Epidemiological Study: materials related to printing of final report, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Epidemiology Study: Supplies (correspondence), 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Estremadoiro, Winston, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ethnobotany, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Estudias Epidemiologicos en Bolivia," Final Report to Peace Corps, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Field work, general information, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Film Production: Filmstrips + Scripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fisher, Phyllis, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Forms: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Forms and Outlines: Epidemiology Study, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Forms and Outlines: Ethnographic Study, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "G" (General Correspondence), 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "H" (General Correspondence), 1966-1967, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Heath, Dr. Dwight B., 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Heath, Dr. Dwight B., undated-1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Heath, Dwight to William McEwen, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Holcomb, Beverly, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "I" (General Correspondence), 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Insurance, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "K" (General Correspondence), 1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Kentucky, University of, Medical College (Dr. Hugh Fullmer), 1965-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Introduction, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "M" (General Correspondence), 1965; 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Microfilm Project, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miller, Solomon, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Minesterio de Salud Publica, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Muratoria, Blanca, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1961-1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - McEwen, Dr. William, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "N" (Correspondence), 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - National Science Foundation Grant Application, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Notes on plants, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Novick, Victor, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Omran, Dr. Abdel R., 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Omran, Dr. Abdel R., 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Omran, Dr. Abdel R. (Epidemiology Study, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "P" (General Correspondence), 1966; 1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Peace Corps: General Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Peace Corps: Public Health Group Terminal Report (Carl A. Moore), 1964 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Peace Corps: Public Health Units, 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Peace Corps: Research Proposal, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Peace Corps: Seminar, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Proposed Bolivia Volunteer Development Corps, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Public Health Service, 1967; 1969 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Quarterly Reports, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Quarterly Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Quarterly Reports (Budget), 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "R" (General Correspondence), 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Reconnaissance, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Reference Publications: "Bolivia's Experiments in Development Without Aid" (Richard W. Patch), 1964 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Reference Publications: "Canton Chullpas, A Socioeconomic Study in the Cochamba Valley of Bolivia" (Olen E. Leonard for the U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1948 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Reference Publications: "Drinking Patterns of the Bolivian Camba" (Dwight B. Heath, Brown University), 1962 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Reference Publications: "El Tifus Exantematico Boliviano o El Tifus Altaplanico" (Instituto Nacional de Bacteriologica), 1935 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Reference Publications: "Santa Cruz: A Socioeconomic Study of an Area in Bolivia" (U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1948 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Releases, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Ressel, Franz, 1964-1970 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Robalina, Elot, 1964-1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Rubin, Dr. Vera (Working Notes), 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "S" (General Correspondence), 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - San Miguel, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Schedules, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "T" (General Correspondence), 1964; 1966-1967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Transportation, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Travel Arrangements and Information, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "U-Z" (General Correspondence), 1966 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 2017 Accretion: "Analisis de La Comunidad Para Accion Comunal", circa 1964-1975 (Box 349, Folder 1)
  - 2017 Accretion: Cross-Cultural Medical Clerkships, 1965-1966 (Box 349, Folder 2)
  - 2017 Accretion: "El Escuerzo y el Aguila: Estratificacion y Cambio Social en una Comunidad Provincial" by William McEwen, Elroy Rogalino S., Katherine B. de Marschall et al., circa 1964-1975 (Box 349, Folder 3)
  - 2017 Accretion: Klein, Lauren, 1965-1966 (Box 349, Folder 4)
  - 2017 Accretion: Rubin, Dr. Vera: Outgoing Correspondence, 1964-1967 (Box 349, Folder 5-12)
  - 2017 Accretion: Rubin, Dr. Vera: Incoming and Outgoing Correspondence, 1971-1978 (Box 349, Folder 13)
- Series II. Accounting Records
- Series III. Indexes, 1964-1967; 127.3 Linear Feet in 7 card boxes and 156 shoe boxes
  Arrangement
  This series has been arranged into two subseries according to type of index: Subseries A. Biographical Index Card and Subseries B. Community Study Outline Indexed Field Notes Card. Cards in the subseries are arranged by community name.
  This series consists of index cards that serve as a quick reference to the original field notes. The Community Study Outline Indexed Field Notes cards were created from photocopies of the field notes that were organized according to coded topics and then cut and pasted onto cards, arranged according to the coded topic. The Biographical Index Cards contain the names of individuals living in each community, their ages, occupations, and place of residence.
  - Subseries A. Biographical Index Cards, 1964-1967; 3.8 Linear Feet in 7 card boxes
    - Compi Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 16)
    - Coroico Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 17)
    - Reyes Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 18)
    - San Miguel Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 19)
    - Sorata Biographical Index Cards A - Z, undated (Box 20)
    - Villa Abecia Biographical Index Cards A - M, undated (Box 21)
    - Villa Abecia Biographical Index Cards N - Z, undated (Box 22)
  - Subseries B. Community Study Outline Indexed Field Notes Cards, 1964-1967; 123.5 Linear Feet in 156 shoe boxes
    - Coroico (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42, Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 46, Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51, Box 52, Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Box 57, Box 58, Box 59, Box 60, Box 61, Box 62, Box 63, Box 64, Box 65, Box 66, Box 67)
    - Reyes (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Box 68, Box 69, Box 70, Box 71, Box 72, Box 73, Box 74, Box 75, Box 76, Box 77, Box 78, Box 79, Box 80, Box 81, Box 82, Box 83, Box 84, Box 85, Box 86, Box 87, Box 88, Box 89, Box 90, Box 91, Box 92, Box 93, Box 95, Box 94, Box 96, Box 97, Box 98, Box 99, Box 100, Box 101)
    - San Miguel (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Box 102, Box 103, Box 104, Box 105, Box 106, Box 107, Box 108, Box 109, Box 110)
    - Sorata (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Box 111, Box 112, Box 113, Box 114, Box 115, Box 116, Box 117, Box 118, Box 119, Box 120, Box 121, Box 122, Box 123, Box 124, Box 125, Box 126, Box 127, Box 128, Box 129, Box 130, Box 131, Box 132, Box 133, Box 134, Box 135, Box 136, Box 137, Box 138, Box 139, Box 140, Box 141, Box 142, Box 143, Box 144, Box 145, Box 146, Box 147, Box 148, Box 149, Box 150, Box 151, Box 152)
    - Villa Abecia (CSO index 1 - 733), undated (Box 153, Box 154, Box 155, Box 156, Box 157, Box 158, Box 159, Box 160, Box 161, Box 162, Box 163, Box 164, Box 165, Box 166, Box 167, Box 168, Box 169, Box 170, Box 171, Box 172, Box 173, Box 174, Box 175, Box 176, Box 177, Box 178)
- Series IV. Epidemiological Research Records, 1963-2003; 18.4 Linear Feet in 28 box binders, 17 manuscript boxes, 3 record cartons, and 2 half manuscript boxes
  Series IV is arranged into eight subseries, as follows:
  Subseries A. Blood Examination Laboratory Processing Records
  Subseries B. Health Questionnaire / Cedula de Salud
  Subseries C. Computer Generated Charts: Census and Distributions
  Subseries D. Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia -- Final Report
  Subseries E. Epidemiological Study Documents
  Subseries F. Blood Samples: Blood Typing Cards
  Subseries G. Investigation of Infant Feeding Habits (100)
  Subseries H. Epidemiological Study Charts
  The materials in this series relate to the epidemiological study conducted between 1964 and 1967. Materials include health questionnaires (cedulas de salud), organized by community name, statistical charts based on the processed census information of the communities being studied, drafts and galleys of the final report and other documents published as a result of this study.
  - Subseries A. Blood Examination Laboratory Processing Records, 1964-1965; 0.4 Linear Feet in 2 half manuscript boxes
    This subseries consists of blood examination laboratory processing records. The material in this series was organized in manuscript form by Dr. Franz Ressel, head of epidemiological laboratory procedures in Bolivia. The test results were indexed by Member of the Household Number.
    - Laboratory records, 1964-1965 (Box 179, Folder 1-4)
    - Laboratory results, 1965 (Box 202, Folder 1, 2-3)
  - Subseries B. Health Questionnaire / Cedula de Salud, 1964-1965; 1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
    This subseries consists of 1,791 health questionnaires (cedulas de salud), organized by community name. The questionnaires were used as a preliminary census that documented the size of households and health conditions of family members. The questionnaires are in Spanish and include information about the family member providing the information, his/her age and health history, and information about the other members of the household. Some of the community files contain health questionnaires and tuberculin surveys. The latter consist of similar information as the healthy questionnaires and include information on tuberculosis titres taken at the time of the survey. The survey focuses on how many people live in the house, on the health of the members of the household, whether anyone in the house was very ill in a set of time not specified on the forms, and what sort of medical treatment that person received. The questionnaires contain the community household number, written above the page numbers, and the name of the head of household, which may also appear in the existing biographical index cards.
    - Cedula de Salud: Compi, 1964-1965 (Box 199, Folder 1-3)
    - Cedula de Salud: Coroico, 1964-1965 (Box 199, Folder 4-7)
    - Cedula de Salud: Reyes, 1964-1965 (Box 199, Folder 8-10)
    - Cedula de Salud: Sorata, 1964-1965 (Box 199, Folder 11-14)
    - Cedula de Salud: Cruz Loma, 1965 (Box 199, Folder 15)
    - Cedula de Salud: Mururata, 1965 (Box 199, Folder 16-17)
    - Cedula de Salud: Bolivar Cruzani, 1965 (Box 199, Folder 18-19)
  - Subseries C. Computer Generated Charts: Census and Distributions, 4 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
    This subseries consists of statistical charts based on the processed census information of the communities being studied. Also included are computer printouts of what appear to be computer programming cards.
    - Computer Card Printouts, 1967-1972 (Box 200, Folder 1-7, Box 348, Box 350, Folder 1-3, Folder 5-6, Folder 8, Box 351, Box 381)
    - Control Cards, 1972 (Box 350, Folder 4, Folder 7)
    - Study Charts and Graphs, 1964-1972 (Box 351, Folder 4)
    - Census Data, 1965 (Box 351, Folder 5-8, Box 201, Folder 1-7, Box 202, Folder 1-4, Box 352, Folder 1-10, Box 353, Folder 1-9)
  - Subseries D. Epidemiological Studies in Bolivia -- Final Report, 1963-2003; 2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons
    This subseries consists of materials related to the final report published in 1967 as Epidemiological Studies in Bolivi a in English and Spanish.
    - Final Report Materials, 1963-2003 (Box 203, Folder 1-16, Box 204, Folder 1-13)
  - Subseries E. Epidemiological Study Documents, 1964-1965; 8 Linear Feet in 17 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
    This subseries contains household administrative cards which include information about people living in each house visited by investigators, which medical tests were administered on them, and a household sanitation survey conducted by the investigators. Each folder contains lab result forms for each household member. The latter includes subjective questions influenced by first world bias, detailing water supply, household cleanliness, presence of insects, and presence of domesticated animals. Also included are tuberculin survey forms and lab result forms for blood and stool tests.
    - Compi, 1964-1965 (Box 205, Folder 1-63, Box 354, Folder 1-74, Box 355, Folder 1-12)
    - Reyes, 1964-1965 (Box 206, Folder 1-60, Box 355, Folder 13-56, Box 356, Folder 1-70, Box 357, Folder 1-31)